{"tossups": [{"question": "The 1st Texas Infantry lost over 80 percent of its men at this battle, the highest regimental casualty rate on either side of the entire war. George Anderson was one of six generals killed at this battle, having suffered a wound while defending the Bloody Lane. This battle, commonly known as Sharpsburg in the South, took place on September 17th, 1862 and resulted in over 22,000 casualties. For ten points, name this battle in Maryland, the bloodiest single-day battle of the Civil War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Antietam</b> (accept Battle of<b> Sharpsburg</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A disaster at this site forced nearby residents to move to the newly constructed city of Slavutych and prompted the construction of an iron sarcophagus to enclose this site. Sweden experienced an incidence of acid rain after a disaster at this site, which is now part of a zone of alienation. The Red Forest was created and Pripyat, Ukraine was rendered uninhabitable by the failure of, for ten points, what Soviet nuclear power plant that melted down in 1986?", "answer": "<b> Chernobyl</b> Nuclear Power Plant (prompt on descriptions of a zone of alienation before mentioned; prompt on too-broad answers like Ukraine before \u201cpower plant\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The rituals of Annaprashana and Mamabhat involve feeding rice to these people. In Japan, the holiday 7-5-3 involves giving these people haircuts. While teaching, Jesus said to bring these people to him and compared them to the ideal kind of faith. A group led by Thomas Muntzer argued against baptizing these people and was known as the Anabaptists. Naming ceremonies are held in honor of, for ten points, what type of people, one of whom is placed in a manger for Christian nativity scenes?", "answer": "<b> child</b>ren (accept equivalents; accept<b> infant</b> or<b> baby</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "In ancient Rome, a man known as the venatore would hunt these animals in herds as a spectacle for commoners. The ancient Greek class of<em> hippeis</em> was named for their ownership of these animals, which were drowned in a river as an offering to Poseidon. Caligula supposedly planned to appoint one of these animals, Incitatus, as consul. The<em> equite</em> [EK-wee-tay] class of Romans owned, for ten points, what animals used to pull chariots?", "answer": "<b> horse</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this war, two generals played a board game called<em> petteia</em> while, unknown to them, a battle raged around them. The Phrygian king Teleutas died in single combat during this war while fighting Ajax, son of Telamon. To avoid fighting in this war, a man pretended to be senile and plowed his field with salt, but gave up the ruse by swerving to avoid his baby son, Telemachus. For ten points, name this ancient war, the subject of Homer\u2019s<em> Iliad</em>.", "answer": "<b> Trojan</b> War", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The 21st specific charge in Richard Nixon\u2019s articles of impeachment concerned a $200,000 bribe to overturn the Price Commission\u2019s ruling on a price increase on this product. Ketchup and mustard are standard on this product, which outperformed a competitor released in the 1980s by the chain A&W because many Americans misunderstood that \u201cone-third\u201d represented a larger, not smaller, fraction. This product is often known as a \u201cRoyal\u201d in countries with the metric system. For ten points, name this larger companion of the Big Mac on the McDonald\u2019s menu.", "answer": "<b> Quarter Pounder</b> (with or without cheese) (prompt on partial answers, like \u201c(McDonald\u2019s) cheeseburger\u201d; do not accept Big Mac)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This group was attacked by \u201chellburners\u201d near Flanders prior to the Battle of Gravelines. A queen declared that she possessed \u201cthe heart and stomach of a king\u201d while rallying resistance against this group in the Tilbury Speech. Sir Francis Drake bragged that he had \u201csinged the beard\u201d of the king after striking this group at Cadiz. Elizabeth I was to be replaced by a Catholic ruler after an attack by, for ten points, what fleet that failed to subdue England in 1588?", "answer": "Spanish<b> Armada</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "At a battle in this state, forces under Sterling Price used bales of water soaked hemp to absorb Union artillery. In addition to the First Battle of Lexington, this state was home to the Battle of Wilson\u2019s Creek, which gave the Confederacy control of its southwestern corner. Bloody Bill Anderson\u2019s bushwhackers carried out the Centralia Massacre in this state, which was admitted to the Union simultaneously with Maine. For ten points, name this state, the subject of an 1820 \u201cCompromise.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Missouri</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This speech warns dictators that \u201cthose who foolishly sought power by riding the back of the tiger ended up inside.\u201d Ted Sorensen helped draft this speech, whose speaker notes that America \u201cshall pay any price [...] to assure the survival and success of liberty.\u201d The challenge to \u201cask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country\u201d was delivered in, for ten points, what January 1961 address?", "answer": "John Fitzgerald<b> Kennedy</b>\u2019s<b> inaugural</b> address (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A global database of incidents of this phenomenon is maintained by the research group START at the University of Maryland. Samuel Scheffler distinguishes \u201cgeneral\u201d and \u201cstate\u201d types of this phenonmenon in a 2006 paper, and Robert Pape analyzes the strategic logic of this phenomenon in his 2005 book<em> Dying</em> <em>to Win</em>. This phenomenon\u2019s name can be traced back to the French Revolution, during the so-called\u201creign\u201d of Robespierre. For ten points, name this phenomenon, broadly defined as intentional violence to coerce or incite fear, as exemplified by the September 11 attacks.", "answer": "<b> terror</b>ism (prompt on generic descriptions of attacks and/or violence)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "In 1731, Ben Franklin founded a subscription-based one of these institutions in Philadelphia. After one of these institutions was destroyed in the British burning of Washington, D.C. during the War of 1812, Thomas Jefferson sold his personal collection to restock it. Over 2,500 of these facilities were built with Andrew Carnegie\u2019s funds. Carnegie helped popularize the \u201copen-shelf\u201d style of, for ten points, what public facilities that include circulation desks and reading rooms?", "answer": "<b> library</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This country\u2019s namesake river passes through its agriculturally rich Fouta region. The MFDC has advocated for the independence of this country\u2019s Casamance region. A holding</b> <b>center for African slaves waiting to be exported operated on this country\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Goree</b> <b>Island. Leopold Sedar Senghor Airport is in this country, the home of the Serer and Wolof ethnic groups. The (*)</b> Gambia is surrounded by, for ten points, what former French colony, an African country with capital at Dakar?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Senegal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man infamously allied his Catholic country with a Protestant nation by signing the Treaty of Barwalde. On the Day of the Dupes, this man nearly lost power when Marie de</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Medici attempted to sway opinion against him. A seawall was constructed to obstruct</b> <b>Medici attempted to sway opinion against him. A seawall was constructed to obstruct</b> <b>shipping to La Rochelle, a (*)</b> <b>shipping to La Rochelle, a (*)</b> Huguenot fortress besieged by this man. This man, who was known as the Red Eminence, served as the adviser of Louis XIII. For ten points, name this French cardinal who was succeeded by Mazarin in 1642.", "answer": "Cardinal<b> Richelieu</b> (or Armand Jean du<b> Plessis</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s Prime Minister was assassinated by disguised electricians during Operation Ogre. This leader, who was given command of the Army of Africa by Emilio Mola, rose to</b> <b>prominence during the (+)</b> <b>prominence during the (+)</b> <b>Rif War in Morocco. This ruler came to power after forming</b> <b>a coalition of the (*)</b> Falange and Carlists to defeat the Republican faction, but he restored the Falange and Carlists to defeat the Republican faction, but he restored the monarchy before his death, leading to the ascension of Juan Carlos I. For ten points, name this fascist dictator of Spain.", "answer": "Francisco<b> Franco</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>An artist from this movement painted</b><em><b> Woman and Child on a Balcony</b></em><b>, whose central figures look toward the golden dome of the Les Invalides hospital and veterans\u201d home.</b> <b>Paintings from this movement, like</b><em><b> In the Wheat</b></em><b>, were painted (+)</b> <b>en plein air and are</b> <b>collected by the Mus\u00b4ee d\u2019Orsay. Berthe Morisot exhibited her work in 1874 alongside a painting of Le Havre, in which (*) </b> hazy ship masts stand quietly in a foggy early morning, that gave this movement its name. For ten points, name this French art movement named for a painting of a <em>Sunrise</em> created by Claude Monet.", "answer": "<b> Impression</b>ism (accept word forms like<b> Impression</b>ist movement; accept<b> Impression, Sunrise</b>; accept<b> Impression, soleil levant</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>One man with this surname was the longest-serving governor of New York and served as Vice President under both Thomas Jefferson and James Madison. Another man with</b> <b>this surname sponsored the construction of the (+)</b> <b>Erie Canal, which was nicknamed his</b> <b>\u201cditch.\u201d In addition to George and DeWitt, another man with this surname signed (*) </b>NAFTA into law and served as the governor of Arkansas; that man came under fire for his affair with the White House intern Monica Lewinsky. For ten points, give this surname shared by politicians Bill and Hillary.", "answer": "<b> Clinton</b> (accept George<b> Clinton</b>, DeWitt<b> Clinton</b>, Bill<b> Clinton</b>, William Jefferson<b> Clinton </b>III, and/or Hillary<b> Clinton</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}